# Derek "Trek" Martin

(208) 298-7563 Derek.reed.martin@gmail.com

#### About Me

Learning is and always has been the guiding star of my life, and I dream about all the new opportunities the world has for me. It is both my means, a skill mastered over countless hours, and my end, to understand the world, its people, its languages, its physics, and endless nuances. This affords me the opportunity to take on new challenges daily, each presenting a new opportunity to grow.

#### Education

Teaching Earth Science (M.A.) TC, Columbia University - July 2022

Business Administration (B.S.)

University of Phoenix - April 2021

Computer Science (B.S.) Neumont University - March 2010

Civil Engineering (B.S.) University of Utah - In Progress

Electrical Engineering (B.S.)

University of Utah - In Progress

Environmental Science (B.S.)

University of Utah - In Progress

#### **Associations**

# United **States Peace Corps Volunteer**

(RPCV)

Peace Corps Volunteers work at the grassroots level to create change that lasts long after their service in a host country. Volunteers make an investment in our world—one handshake, one project, one friendship at a time—that leads to new possibilities

### **PCV Media** (Journalist/Editor)

Youtube channel dedicated to teaching the public about the work and experience of being a Peace Corps Volunteer. My work took me all over Ghana, interviewing volunteers and community members and developing stories

### **HackManhattan** (Member)

Hackmanhattan is a non-profit, all-volunteer makerspace in Midtown, Manhattan. It's a place for engineers and artists to pursue and explore ideas and public engagement in STEM literacy

## National Science Teacher Association (Member)

Community of science educators that choose to extend beyond the classroom, together striving to influence and advance change in science literacy and access

## **Employment**

# Teacher, Earth Science Celia Cruz Bronx High School of Music

January 2022 - July 2022

## Teacher, Coding •

Robofun March 2021 - January 2022

## Teacher, English

March 2020 - March 2021

## Teacher, Coding

The Coding Space June 2019 - March 2020

# Teacher, Math/Science/English •

U.S. Peace Corps, Ghana May 2017 - June 2019

# Software Engineer, I - III — CHG Healthcare Group inc., Spiral Solutions

March 2010 - March 2017

### Role Details

Student teacher at low-income/high needs magnet school for students graduating a summer music program. Developed curriculum, taught lessons, encouraged engagement through lessons on using 3d printing.

Teaching coding to youth, ages 7-12. Taught in small groups using legos, Minecraft, etc, to encourage STEM literacy. My position was with 'grant' contracts, meaning I taught in low-income schools as part of government grant programs.

Taught Japanese high school level English and Eiken (English proficiency) test prep in public high school. Designed curriculum. Once a week, taught at a special needs schools, ages 5-18

Teaching computer programming, ages 8-18 in groups of 8-16. Collaborate with coteachers, developing curriculum, addressing management issues, and counseling with parents.

Taught Mathematics and Science in a small village. Lead outreach efforts in literacy, DEI, and vocational development. Afterschool program for pregnant/mother girls to prepare for HS equivalency

Technical lead for a small team, leading design direction, interfacing with U.S. military clients Developed documentation, and trained clientele Produced marketing videos for various campaigns

### Special Skills

resin art/casts, mineral/gemstone polishing, programming, D&D DM'ing, game design, web design, electronics, microcontrollers, video production, cinematography, editing, drawing, digital painting, paludarium construction, gardening, food technology, cooking, baking, woodworking, 3d printing, wet processing (peanut butter, chocolate, rice pudding, curry)

### Fun Facts

**Board Game and Music Video Collector** Lived and Worked in Three Countries **Speaks Conversational Japanese** and Child-Level Chinese Collector of Vocational Skills Liked the End of Lost,